# Tyom Semonov

# Frontend Developer

A passionate developer with over 13 years of professional experience in building high-traffic complex websites and applications using web standards and best practices for desktops and mobile devices.

Great attention to detail, code maintainability and performance. A keen learner. Advocate of datadriven, user-centred, accessible, mobile-first design.

#### Core skills

- JavaScript
- Node.js
- Webpack
- Express
- React
- CSS/PostCSS/Sass
- HTML5
- Accessibility
- Git
- Photoshop, Illustrator, Sketch

#### **Current focus**

- Node.js
- Express
- React/Redux
- Vue JS

github.com/tyom



in linkedin.com/in/tyoms

+44 7984 695 623 tyom@semonov.com

# **EXPERIENCE**

October 2017 - November 2017

# **BCG Digital Ventures**

Senior Frontend Engineer CONTRACTOR

Short lived project where within a small team I was actively involved in building dashboard UI for displaying and interacting with data for a large cement producer.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (React, Redux, Jest, Webpack), CSS Modules, Git

May 2017 - October 2017

## Department for International Trade (DIT)

Senior Frontend Developer CONTRACTOR

Was instrumental in driving forward the development of a complex CRM tool for the department. Building the application with wide range of browser support (including legacy). Innovating within constraints to fulfil the user needs, improve development tools and processes.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (Vanilla, node.js, Express, Webpack, Mocha, Nightwatch JS, Nunjucks), Sass, Git

November 2016 - April 2017

## **NHS Digital**

Senior Frontend Developer CONTRACTOR

Working in a team on transformation of NHS.UK. Created and maintained common components library which documents and shows usage of various components that make various NHS.UK online services, such as beta.nhs.uk. It is currently being used by several services.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (node.js, Express, Webpack, Gulp, Mocha), Sass, Git, Fractal (component library)

## July 2016 - November 2016

# **Barclays**

Senior Frontend Developer CONTRACTOR

Principal front-end developer working on internal tool for managing risks in agile development of projects within the bank.

Responsible for ensuring that the application is meeting Barclays standards for accessibility and usability. Introduced a number of frontend best practices the team. Optimised and improved maintainability of the front-end codebase.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (Angular JS, Webpack), Unit testing (Jasmine, Karma, Spock), CSS/Less, Git, Jenkins

#### December 2015 - June 2016

#### **BBC**

Senior JavaScript Application Developer CONTRACTOR

Working in a small team responsible for launching the BBC Three online service.

Building isomorphic BBC Three components in React and BBC Morph modules in node.js. Using BBC GEL design framework with focus on reusability, unit/acceptance testing, performance and consistent cross-device/browser experience.

Designed and built a number of BBC Three specific features as well as taking an opportunity to improve performance/organisation of existing code.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (React JS, Node.js, Express, Gulp, Webpack), Unit testing (Mocha, skin-deep, React Shallow Render, Web Driver, BrowserStack, Galen Framework), CSS/PostCSS, Git/Github, Jenkins

#### September 2014 - December 2015

## **UK Ministry of Justice**

Developer CONTRACTOR

Responsible for front-end development and design of Civil Legal Advice public website. Continuous development of functional prototypes used in rounds of user-testing to test hypothesis and validate design decisions. Maintained an AngularJS call-centre application.

Developed component libraries and generated service style guides. Built NPM packages to ease the exchange and development of assets and components across government websites and web applications.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (Vanilla, node.js, AngularJS, Nightwatch, Gulp, Webpack), CSS/Sass, Ruby (Rails, Middleman), Python (Django, Flask, Jinja), Git/Github, Jenkins, Graphviz, Google Analytics, Sketch

#### May 2012 - September 2014

#### state.com

Frontend Developer

Working in a team of four. Responsible for development and maintenance of public site and internal applications. Primarily working with Ruby, node.js, Sass, HTML5 and JavaScript running on AWS.

Leading the development and management of scalable modular stylesheet architecture for State's platform. Developed methodology and processes for management of complex stylesheets which allows efficient reuse of components across various products.

Regularly built functional prototypes for usability testing. Made large contributions to component server for testing, development and presentation of complex interfaces which allows interactive testing of each interface component in isolation.

Managed a large number of cross-client email templates. Built tools for their creation and testing (integrated with MailChimp API), used by the whole team.

Redesigned site's admin panel (Rails) and API documentation.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (Vanilla, Dojo, AMD, node.js, AngularJS, Buster.js, D3, Grunt), CSS/Sass, SVG, Ruby (Rails, Middleman), Git/Github, MongoDB, Redis, Photoshop/Illustrator

January 2012 - May 2012

## **VisualDNA**

Frontend Developer

Responsible for initial development of internal Quiz Editor rich application, intended to replace legacy application that was managing all of company's quizzes.

## **Technologies**

JavaScript/CoffeeScript (jQuery, Backbone.js), CSS, PHP (Twig), SVN/Git, Photoshop

January 2012 - May 2012

## streetlife.com

Designer/Developer

Joined the team of one back-end developer, and two founders. Assumed responsibilities of designer and full-stack developer. Built initial prototypes and led the research and design of the product (Information Architecture, sketches and wireframes, prototypes, visual design, and full front-end implementation). The site rapidly grew to tens of thousands of active users and hundreds of communities in the UK and featured across British media.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (jQuery), CSS, Python (Django, Flask, Jinja2), Vagrant, Puppet, Git/Github Photoshop/Illustrator, OmniGraffle

January 2010 - February 2010

# DigitasLBi

Interface Developer CONTRACTOR

Worked in small team of designers and developers on redesign of discoverireland.ie.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript (jQuery), CSS, HTML, Photoshop

#### December 2007 - November 2009

#### **Microsoft**

**UX** Designer

Worked in a medium size team on Bing Maps UK as a UX researcher and developer. Created interactive prototypes and conducted usability tests to help shape decisions on product direction. Worked with other software engineers to deliver a number features for high-traffic Bing Maps. Including UI for Bird's Eye view, public transit information, printable and shareable maps.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript, HTML/XML, CSS, Script#, C#, Photoshop/Illustrator

# September 2006 - December 2007

# Multimap

Web Developer

Joined the development team as one of the core developers, redesigning a website featuring complex and interactive standards-based web interface. Responsible for the majority of new stylesheets and markup. Restyling of all map interface elements for the public API and website with full cross-browser support.

#### **Technologies**

JavaScript, CSS, HTML, Perl, Template Toolkit, Perforce, Photoshop/Illustrator

September 2006 - December 2007

# **Sportingbet**

Web Developer

Working in a multilingual team of developers. Rebuilt table-based Russian website with web standards and best practices, greatly improving performance and maintainability. Promoted web standards across the team. Maintained internal Wiki to share best practices, assets and resources. Designed mobile UI elements.

## **Technologies**

HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Wikimedia, Photoshop

# February 2004 - October 2005

# Freelancing

Design, Development

Worked on a number of projects ranging from wireframes, websites, CMS integrations and design (branding and promotional material).

#### **Technologies**

HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, Photoshop, Illustrator and others

# **EDUCATION**

1997 - 2000 (Ukraine)

**Sumy State University** 

Linguistics and Translation